you
Krishnamurti in dialogue with Dr. Alan
W. Anderson. J. Krishnamurti was born in
South India and educated in England. For
the past 40 years he has been speaking
in the United States, Europe, India,
Australia, and other parts of the world.
From the outset of his life's
work he repudiated all connections with
organized religions and ideologies and said
that his only concern was to set
men absolutely unconditionally free. He is
the author of many books, among them
The Awakening of Intelligence, The Urgency
of Change, Freedom from the Known, and
The Flight of the Eagle. This is
one of a series of dialogues between Krishnamurti
and Dr. Alan W. Anderson, who
is professor of religious studies at San
Diego State University where he teaches
Indian and Chinese scriptures and the
oracular tradition. Dr. Anderson, a
published poet, received his degree from
Columbia University and the Union
Theological Seminary. He has been honored
with a Distinguished Teaching Award
from the California State Universities.
Mr. Krishnamurti, in our last
conversation together we had moved from
speaking together concerning fear and
the relation between that and
transformation of the individual person which
is not dependent on knowledge or
time and then from that we went to
pleasure and just as we reached the end
of the conversation the question of
beauty arose and if it's agreeable with
you I should like very much
for us to explore that together.
One often wonders why museums are
so filled with pictures and statues.
Is it because man has lost touch with
nature and therefore has to go to these
museums to look at other people's
paintings, famous paintings, and some of
them are really marvellously beautiful. Why
do the museums exist at all?
I'm just asking, I'm not saying they
should or should not. And I've been to
many museums all over the world, taken around by experts.
And I've always felt as
though I was being shown around
and looking at things that were
so, for me, artificial, so other people's
expression, what they consider beauty,
and I wondered what is beauty?
Because when you read a poem of Keats
or some really a poem that a man writes
with his heart and with very deep
feeling, he wants to convey something to
you of what he feels, what he
considers to be the most exquisite essence of
beauty. And I've looked at great many
cathedrals, as you must have, over Europe,
and again this expression of
their feelings, their devotion, their reverence
to in masonry, in rock, in buildings,
in marvellous cathedrals, and looking at all
this, I'm always surprised when people
talk about beauty or write about beauty
whether it is something created by man or
something that you see in nature, or it has
nothing to do with the stone or with
the paint or with the word, but something deeply
ingood. And so, often in discussing
with so-called professionals, having a dialogue
with them, it appears to me that it
is always somewhere out there, the modern painting,
modern music, the pop, and so on,
so on, it's always somehow so dreadfully artificial.
I may be wrong, but so what is
beauty? Must it be expressed? That's one question.
Does it need the word, the stone, the
colour, the paint, or it is something that cannot
possibly be expressed in word, in a building, in
a statue? So, if we could go into this
question of what is beauty, I feel to really
go into it very deeply, one must know what
is suffering, or understand what is suffering,
because without passion you can't have beauty.
Passion in the sense, not lust, not the
passion that comes when there is immense suffering,
and the remaining with that suffering, not
escaping from it, brings this passion. Perhaps?
And passion means the abandonment, the complete abandonment
of the me, of the self, the ego,
and therefore a great austerity, not the austerity
of – as the word means – ash,
severe, dry, which the religious people have
made into, but rather the austerity of great
beauty.
A. Yes, I am following you, I really am.
A great sense of dignity, beauty, that
is essentially austere. And to be austere, not
verbally or ideologically, but being austere,
means total abandonment, letting go of the
me. And one cannot let that thing take
place if one hasn't deeply understood what suffering
is. Because passion comes from the word sorrow.
I don't know if you have looked into that
word. The root meaning of the
word passion is sorrow, from suffering.
A. To feel.
To feel. You see, sir, people have escaped
from suffering. I think it is very deeply
related to beauty. Not that you must
suffer. I don't know if I am...
A. Not that you must suffer, but...
No, we must go a little more slowly. I
am jumping too quickly. First of all, we assume
we know what beauty is. We see Picasso
or Rembrandt or Michelangelo, and we think, how
marvellous that is. We think we know. We
have read it in books, experts have written about
it, and so on. One reads and says, yes,
we absorb it through others. But if one was
really enquiring into what is beauty, there must
be a great sense of humility. I don't
know what beauty is, actually. I can imagine
what beauty is. I have learnt what beauty
is. I have been taught in schools, in
colleges, reading books and going on tours, guided tours
and all the rest, visiting thousand museums. But
actually, to find out the depth of beauty,
the depth of colour, the depth of feeling,
the mind must start with great sense of humility.
I don't know. Really, one doesn't know
what meditation is. One thinks, one knows. When
we discuss meditation, we'll come... So, one must
start, I feel, if one is enquiring into
beauty with great sense of humility, not
knowing. That very not knowing is beauty.
A. Yes, yes. I have been listening and I
have been trying to open myself to this relation
that you are making between beauty and passion. And...
K. You see, sir, let's start. Man
suffers, not only personally, but there is immense
suffering of man. It is a thing that
is pervading the universe. Man has suffered physically,
psychologically, spiritually, in every way for
centuries upon centuries. The mother cries
because her son is killed. The mother cries
or the wife cries because her husband is being
mutilated in a war. Or there is tremendous
suffering in the world. I don't think people
are aware or even feel this immense sorrow
that is in the world. They are so concerned
with their own personal sorrow, they overlook the
sorrow that a poor man in a little village
in India or in China or in the Eastern
world, will never possibly have a full meal, clean
clothes, comfortable bed. And there is the
sorrow of thousands of people being killed
in war or in the totalitarian world,
millions being executed for ideologies, tyranny, the
terror of all that. So there is all this
sorrow in the world. And there is also the personal
sorrow. And without really understanding it
very, very, very deeply and resolving it,
passion won't come out of sorrow. And without
passion, how can you see beauty? You can intellectually
appreciate a painting or a poem or a statue,
but you need this great sense of inward bursting
of passion, exploding of passion. That creates
in itself the sensitivity that can say beauty.
So it is, I think, rather important to
understand sorrow. I think it is related beauty, passion,
sorrow.
A. I am interested in the order of those
words, beauty, passion, sorrow. If one is, in relation
to the transformation we have been speaking about, to
come to beauty, I take it as a passage
from sorrow to passion to beauty.
Yes, please do go on. I understand.
K. You see, in the Christian world, if I
am not mistaken, sorrow is delegated to a person.
We either take that person or we somehow escape
from sorrow, or at least we hope to escape
from sorrow. And in the Eastern world,
sorrow is rationalised through the statement of karma.
You know the word karma means to do. And
they believe in karma. That is what you have done
in your past life, you pay for it in the present
or reward it in the present, and so on and so on.
So there are these two categories of escapes.
And there are a thousand escapes – whiskey,
sex, going off to attend the mass and so on
and so on. Man has never stayed with a thing.
He has always either sought comfort in a
belief, in an action, in identification with something
greater than himself and so on and so on, but
he has never said, look, I must see what this is.
I must penetrate it and not delegate it to somebody
else. I must go into it, I must face it,
I must look at it, I must know what it
is. So when the mind doesn't escape from this sorrow,
either personal or the sorrow of man,
if you don't escape, if you don't rationalise,
if you don't try to go beyond it, if you
are not frightened of it, then you remain with it.
Because any movement from what is, any movement
away from what is, is a dissipation of energy.
It prevents you actually understanding what
is. The what is is sorrow.
And we have means and
ways and cunning, development of escapes.
Now, if there is no escape
whatsoever, then you remain with it.
I don't know if you have ever done it.
Because in every one's life there is an
incident that brings you tremendous sorrow, a happening.
It might be an incident, a word, an accident,
a shattering sense of absolute loneliness, and so on.
These things happen, and with that
comes this sense of utter sorrow.
Now, when the mind can remain with that, not
move away from it, out of that comes passion.
Not the cultivated passion, not
the artificial trying to be passionate,
but the movement of passion is
born out of this non-withdrawal from sorrow.
It is the total, completely remaining with that.
A. I am thinking that we also say, when
we speak of someone in sorrow, that they are disconsolate.
K. Yes, disconsolate.
A. Disconsolate. And immediately we think that the antidote
to that is to get rid of the disc,
not to stay with the disc.
And in an earlier conversation we spoke
about two things related to each other
in terms of opposite sides of the same coin.
And while you've been speaking, I've been seeing the
interrelation in a polar sense between action and passion.
Action being able to undergo, able to be
changed, whereas action is doing to effect change.
And this would be the movement from
sorrow to passion at the precise point,
if I've understood you correctly, where I
become able to undergo what is there.
So, when there is no escape, when there is
no desire to seek comfort away from what is,
then out of that absolute inescapable
reality comes this flame of passion.
And without that there is no beauty.
You may write endless volumes about
beauty, or be a marvellous painter,
but without that inward quality of passion,
which is the outcome of great understanding of sorrow,
I don't see how beauty can exist.
Also, one observes, man has lost touch with nature.
A. Oh, yes.
K. Completely, especially in big towns.
And even in small towns or
hamlets, man is always outwardly going, outward,
pursued by his own thoughts.
And so he has more
or less lost touch with nature.
Nature means nothing to him.
Yes, it's very nice, very beautiful.
Once I was standing with a few
friends and my brother many years ago
over Grand Canyon, looking at the morns, incredible,
the colours, the depth and the shadows,
and a group of people came and one lady says,
yes, isn't this marvellous?
And the next day she
says, let's go and have tea.
And off they trotted.
That took her.
That is what is happening in the world.
We have lost completely touch with nature.
We don't know what it means.
And also we kill. You follow?
We kill for food, we kill for amusement,
we kill what is called for sport.
I won't go into all that.
So there is this lack of intimate relationship with nature.
I remember a shock, a profound shock
that I had in my college days.
I was standing on the steps of the administration building
and watching a very, very beautiful sunset.
And one of my college quents
asked me what I was doing.
And I said, well, I'm not doing anything,
I'm looking at the sunset.
And you know what he said to me?
This so shocked me that it's one of those things
that you never forget.
He just said, well, there is
nothing to prevent it, is there?
Nothing?
Nothing to prevent it, is there?
Right, right.
Yes, I know, I follow you.
So, sir, you see, we
are becoming more and more artificial,
more and more superficial,
more and more verbal,
a linear direction,
neither vertical, not vertical at all, but linear.
And so naturally, artificial things become more important,
theatres, cinemas,
you know, the whole business of the modern world.
And very few have this sense of beauty in themselves,
beauty in conduct.
You understand, sir?
A. Oh, yes.
K. Beauty in behaviour,
beauty in the usage of their language, the voice,
the manner of walking, the sense of humility,
with that humility everything becomes so gentle, quiet,
full of beauty.
We have none of that.
And yet we go to museums, you know,
we are educated with museums, with pictures,
and we have lost the delicacy, the sensitivity
of the mind, the heart, the body.
And so when we have lost
the sensitivity, how can we be,
how can we know what beauty is?
And when we haven't got sensitivity,
we go off to some
place to learn to be sensitive.
You know that.
A. No, I do.
K. Go to a college or some ashrama
or some rotten hole,
and there I am going to learn to be sensitive.
Sensitive through touch, through...
A. Yes.
K. That becomes disgusting.
Now how can we, as
you are a professor and teacher,
how can you, sir, educate
– it becomes really very important –
the students to have this quality?
Therefore one asks, what is it we are educated for?
What are we being educated for?
Everybody is being educated.
Ninety percent of the people probably in America
are being educated,
know what to read and write
and all the rest of it.
What for?
A. And yet it is a
fact, at least in my experience
of teaching class after class, year after year,
that with all this proliferation of publishing
and so-called educational techniques,
students are without as much care
to the written word and the spoken word
as was the case that
I can distinctly remember years ago.
Now perhaps other teachers have had a different experience,
but I have watched this in my classes.
And the usual answer that I get
when I speak to my colleagues about this is,
well, the problem is in the high schools.
And then you talk to a poor high school.
K. And then it is put out into the school.
A. And then he puts
it on the poor grade school.
So we have poor grade school, poor high school,
poor college, poor university,
because we are always picking up where we left off,
which is a little lower next
year from where it was before.
K. Sir, that is why
I have talked in various universities
and so on and so on.
I have always felt, what are we being educated for?
To just become glorified clerks?
A. Well, that is what it turns out to be.
K. Of course it is.
Glorified businessmen, or God knows what else.
What for?
I mean, if I have a son,
that would be a tremendous problem for me.
Fortunately, I haven't got sick,
but it would be a burning question to me,
what am I to do
with the children that I have?
To centralise all these schools
where they are taught nothing but just
how to read and write
a book and how to memorise
and forget the whole field of life.
They are taught about sex and reproduction,
all that kind of stuff, but what?
So I feel, sir, I mean,
to me this is a tremendous,
the important question,
is what is the point of education?
To me this is a tremendous, the important question,
because I am concerned with several schools in India,
and in England there is one,
we are going to form one here in California.
It is a burning question,
what is it that we are doing with our children?
Making them into another robot,
or into other clever cunning clerks,
great scientists who will invent this or that
and then be ordinary cheap little human beings?
Sod the minds? You follow, sir?
A. I am, I am, I am.
K. So when you talk about beauty,
can we, can a human being tell another,
educate another to grow in beauty,
grow in goodness,
to flower in great affection, care?
Because if we don't do that,
we are destroying the earth as it is happening now,
polluting the air.
We human beings are destroying everything we touch.
So this becomes a very, very serious thing
when we talk about beauty,
when we talk about pleasure, fear,
relationship, order and so on, all that,
none of these things are being taught in any school.
A. No, I brought that up in my class yesterday,
and I asked them directly that very question,
and they were very ready
to agree that here we are,
we are in an upper division course,
and we have never heard about this.
K. Tragic, you follow, sir?
A. And furthermore, we don't know
whether we are really hearing
it for what it really is,
because we haven't heard about it.
We have got to go through that yet
to find out whether we are really listening.
K. And whether the teacher or
the man who is a professor
is honest enough to say, look, I don't know,
I am going to learn about all this.
So, sir, that is why Western civilisation
– I am not condemning
it, I am observing it –
Western civilisation is mainly concerned
with commercialism, consumerism
and a society that is immoral.
And when we talk about the transformation of man,
not in the field of knowledge
or in the field of time,
but beyond that,
who are interested in this?
You follow, sir? Who really cares about it?
Because the mother goes off to earn a job,
earn a livelihood, the father goes off,
and the child is just an incident.
Now, as a matter of fact,
I know this will probably appear
like an astonishingly extravagant statement for me to make,
but I think it is getting to the place now
where if anyone raises this question
at the level that you have been raising it,
as a young person, say,
growing up in his adolescent years,
as I say, and he won't let it go,
he hangs in there with it, as we say,
the question is seriously raised whether he is normal.
Yes, quite, quite, quite.
And it makes one think of Socrates,
who was very clear that he knew only one thing
that he didn't know,
and he didn't have to say that very often,
but he said it even the
few times enough to get him killed,
but at least they took
him seriously enough to kill him.
Today I think he would be
put in some institution for study.
The whole thing would have to be checked out.
That's what is happening in Russia.
They send him off to an asylum,
mental hospital, and destroy him.
Sir, here we neglect everything
for some superficial gain.
Money.
Money means power, position, authority, everything, money.
It goes back to the
success thing that you mentioned before.
Always later, always later,
on the horizontal axis.
But when you... excuse me.
I did want to share with you,
as you were speaking about nature,
something that has a sort of wry humour about it
in terms of the history of scholarship.
I thought of those marvellous Vedic hymns to dawn,
which, Dakshinara, that the way dawn comes,
rosy-fingered,
and scholars have expressed surprise
that the number of hymns
to her are, by comparison, few,
compared with some other gods.
But the attention is drawn in the study,
not to the quality of the hymn,
as revealing how it is that
there are such consummately beautiful cadences
associated with her,
for which you'd only need one, wouldn't you?
You wouldn't need twenty-five.
The important thing is, isn't it remarkable
that we have so few hymns,
and yet they're so wonderfully beautiful?
What has the number to do with it at all?
It is the thing that I
could never get answered for myself
in terms of the environment in which I studied
Sanskrit and the Veda.
The important thing is to find out which god,
which is Indra, is in the Rig Veda,
mentioned most often.
Now, of course, I'm not trying to suggest
that quantity should be overlooked by no means,
but if the question had been approached
the way you have been inquiring into it,
deeper, deeper, deeper,
then I think scholarship would have had
a very, very different career.
We should have been taught how to sit
and let that hymn disclose itself,
and stop measuring it.
Yes, sir.
Yes, please, please do go on.
That's what I was going to say.
You see, when discussing beauty and passion and sorrow,
we ought to go into the question also,
what is action?
Yes.
Because it is related to all that.
Yes, of course.
What is action?
Because life is action,
living is action,
speaking is action, everything is action.
Sitting here is an action,
talking, a dialogue, discussing, going into things,
is a series of actions, a movement in action.
So, what is action?
Action obviously means acting now,
not having acted or will act.
It is the active present
of the word act, to act,
which is acting all the time.
Otherwise there is no...
it is a movement in time and out of time.
We will go into that a little bit later.
Now, so what is action that does not bring sorrow?
You follow?
One has to put that question,
because every action, as we do now,
is either regret, contradiction,
a sense of meaningless movement,
a repression, conformity and so on.
So that is action for most people.
The routine, the repetition,
the remembrance of things past
and act according to that remembrance.
So, unless one understands very deeply what is action,
one will not be able to understand what is sorrow.
So, action, sorrow, passion and beauty.
They are all together, not divorced,
not something separate,
beauty is at the end, action is at the beginning.
It isn't like that at
all, it is all one thing.
But to look at it, what is action?
As far as one knows now,
action is according to a formula,
according to a concept, or according to an ideology,
the communist ideology, the capitalist ideology,
or socialist ideology,
or the ideology of a Christian, Jesus, Christ,
or the Hindu with his ideologies.
So, action is the approximation
of an idea.
I act according to my concept.
That concept is traditional,
or put together by me,
or put together by an expert.
Lenin, Marx have formulated,
and they conform according to what they think Lenin, Marx,
and action is according to a pattern.
You follow?
A. Yes, I do.
What is occurring to me is that
under the tyranny of that one is literally driven.
K. Absolutely.
Driven, conditioned, brutalised.
You don't care for anything except for ideas,
and carrying out ideas.
See what is happening in China, in Russia.
A. Yes, I do.
K. And here too the
same thing in a modified form.
So, action as we know it now
is conformity to a pattern,
either in the future or in the past,
an idea which I carry out,
a resolution or a decision which I fulfil in acting.
The past is acting.
So it is not action.
I don't know if you understand.
A. Yes, I am aware of the fact that
we suffer a radical conviction
that if we don't generate a pattern,
there will be no order.
K. You follow what is happening, sir?
Order is in terms of a pattern.
A. Yes, preconceived. Yes.
K. Therefore it is disorder
against which an intelligent mind fights,
fights in the sense, revolves.
So that is why it is very important
if we are to understand what beauty is,
if we are to understand what action is.
Can there be action without the idea?
Idea means, you must know from Greek,
means to see, see what we have done, sir.
The word is to see.
That is, seeing and the doing,
not the seeing, draw a conclusion from that
and then act according to that conclusion.
You see?
A. Oh yes, yes.
K. Perceiving from that perception,
draw a belief, an idea, a formula,
and act according to that belief, idea, formula.
So we are removed from perception.
We are acting only according to a formula,
therefore mechanical.
You see, sir, how our minds have become mechanical.
A. Necessarily so. K. Obviously.
A. I just thought about Greek sculpture
and its different character from Roman sculpture.
The finest of ancient Greek sculpture
is extremely contemplative.
It has sometimes been remarked
that the Romans had a genius for portraiture in stone.
K. Law and order and all that.
A. Yes, and of course one would see
their remarkable attention to personality.
But what occurred to me
while I was listening to this,
something that had never occurred to me before,
that the Greek statue with which one sometimes asks himself,
well, the face doesn't disclose a personality.
Perhaps the quiet eye recognized
that you don't put onto the stone
something that must come out of the act itself.
K. Quite, quite.
A. Because you're doing something
that you must wait to come to pass.
The Greeks were correct.
It's an expression of that relation to form,
which is an interior form.
Marvellous grasp of that.
It's a grasp that allows for splendour to break out
rather than the notion that we must represent it.
Yes, I am following you, aren't I?
K. You see, sir, that's why
one must ask this essential question,
what is action?
Is it a repetition?
Is it imitation?
Is it an adjustment between what is
and what should be or what has been?
Or is it a conformity to a pattern,
or to a belief, or to a formula?
If it is, then inevitably there must be conflict.
Because idea, action, there is an interval,
a lag of time between the two,
and in that interval a great many things happen,
a division in which other incidents take place,
and therefore there must be inevitably conflict,
because action is never complete.
Action is never total, it is never ending.
Action means ending.
You know, you used the word Vedanta the other day.
It means the ending of knowledge, I was told.
Not the continuous of knowledge, but the ending.
That is, the freedom, all that.
Now, is there an action
which is not tied to the past as time,
or to the future,
or to a formula, or to
a belief, or to an idea,
but action?
The seeing is the doing.
A. Yes.
K. The seeing is the doing
becomes an extraordinary movement in freedom.
The other is not freedom.
And therefore, sir, the communists say
there is no such thing as freedom.
That is a bourgeois idea.
Of course it is, bourgeois idea,
because they live in ideas, concepts, not in action.
They live according to ideas
and carry those ideas out in action,
which is not action, the doing.
I don't know...
A. Oh, yes, yes, I was just thinking...
K. And this is what
we do in the Western world,
in the Eastern world, and all over the world,
is acting according to a formula, idea,
belief, a concept, a conclusion, a decision.
And never the seeing and the doing.
A. I was thinking about the cat,
the marvellous animal, the cat.
Its face is almost all eye.
I don't mean that by
measure, with calipers, of course not.
And we don't train cats
like we try to train dogs.
I think we have corrupted dogs.
Cats won't be corrupted.
They simply won't be corrupted.
And it seems to me a
great irony that in the Middle Ages
we should have burned cats along with witches.
K. The ancient Egyptians worshipped cats.
A. Yes. The great eye of the cat.
I read some time ago that the cat's skeletal structure
is among mammals the most perfectly adapted to its function.
K. Correct.
A. I think one of the most profound occasions
for gratitude in my life
was the living with a cat.
And she taught me how to make an end.
But I went through a lot of interior agony
before I came to understand what she was doing.
It's as though one would say of her
that she was performing a mission, we might say,
without, of course, being a missionary
in the ordinary sense of the word.
Yes, yes.
K. Yes, sir. You see,
one begins to see what freedom is in action.
A. That's right.
K. And the seeing in the doing
is prevented by the observer
who is the past, the formula, the concept, the belief.
That observer comes in between perception and the doing.
That observer is the factor of division,
the idea and the conclusion in action.
So, can we act only when there is perception?
We do this, sir, when we
are at the edge of a precipice.
The seeing danger is instant action.
A. If I remember correctly, the
word alert comes from the Italian,
which points to standing at the edge of a cliff.
K. Cliff. That's right.
A. That's pretty serious.
K. You see, but it's very interesting.
We are conditioned to danger of a cliff,
of a snake, or a dangerous animal, and so on.
We are conditioned.
But we are not conditioned to...
and we are conditioned also to this idea
that you must act according to an idea,
otherwise there is no action.
A. No, we are conditioned to that.
Terribly so.
K. So we are conditioned to danger
and conditioned to the fact
that you cannot act without a formula,
without a concept, belief, and so on.
So these two are the factors of our conditioning.
And now someone comes along and says,
look, that's not action,
that's merely a repetition of what has been,
modified, but it's not action.
Action is when you see and do.
A. And the reaction to that is,
oh, I see, he has a new definition of action.
K. No, no, no. Yes. I'm not defining.
A. Yes, of course not.
K. I mean, I've done this all my life.
I see something and I do it.
Say, for instance, as you may know,
I'm not being personal or anything,
but a great big organisation,
spiritual organisation with thousands of followers,
with a great deal of land, five thousand acres,
castles, and money, and so on,
were formed around me, as a board.
And in 1928 I said, this is all wrong,
I dissolved it,
returned the property and so on.
I saw how wrong it was, the seeing,
not the conclusions, comparisons,
how religions have done, I saw and acted.
A. Exactly.
K. And therefore there has never been a regret.
A. Marvellous.
K. Never been said,
oh, I made a mistake, sir,
because I shall have nobody to lean on.
You follow? A. Yes, I do.
Could we next time, in our next conversation,
relate beauty to seeing?
That was splendid.
K. Oh, splendid, yes, that's wonderful.